<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-23T05:51:28+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">New workshop on parliamentary data at the Swedish Riksdag (August 28–29)</title><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2024/New-workshop-on-parliamentary-data-at-the-Swedish-Riksdag-(August-28-29)/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New workshop on parliamentary data at the Swedish Riksdag (August 28–29)"/><published>2024-05-28T00:44:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-28T00:44:16+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2024/New-workshop-on-parliamentary-data-at-the-Swedish-Riksdag-(August-28%E2%80%9329)</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2024/New-workshop-on-parliamentary-data-at-the-Swedish-Riksdag-(August-28-29)/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://github.com/swerik-project/swerik-project.github.io/assets/15212990/f496a554-c59f-4f04-8896-aa4640dcd6a7" alt="text-mining-43255resize25601600crop002560800autoorientquality90density150stripextensionjpgid25 (1)"/></p> <p>Last fall, the Swerik project, in collaboration with the CLARIN-ERIC, gathered researchers and other stakeholders at the Swedish Riksdag and had a productive workshop on researching the digitized Swedish parliamentary documents. Among the speakers were Jan Teorell (Stockholm University), Nina Tahmasebi (Gothenburg University), and Pelle Snickars (Lund University). The event was appreciated, especially the discussions of, for example, how to simultaneously build infrastructure and use it for research, as well as how to collaborate between researchers and non-university institutions.</p> <p><strong>On August 28–29, the Swerik project organizes a follow-up workshop on the same theme</strong>. The purpose is foremost to provide both doctoral students and early-career scholars and senior researchers with a forum to discuss research ideas, results, and challenges related to Swedish parliamentary data. Moreover, the ambition is to create a network of researchers working on parliamentary sources.</p> <p>The workshop is organized as a lunch-to-lunch event. The first day is dedicated to research presentations by senior scholars and institutions that facilitate parliamentary data that in various ways collaborate with the Swerik project. We end the first day with dinner at Movitz in Old Town. The second day is planned as another session of presentations by junior scholars. <strong>If you wish to submit a proposal for a presentation on the second day, please send an abstract (ca 200 words, excl. a short bio).</strong></p> <p><strong>Registrations, abstract, and questions: fredrik.noren@mau.se.</strong></p> <p><em>Confirmed speakers on the first day of the workshop:</em></p> <p><strong>Hanna Bäck</strong> (Lund University): “Studying political polarization in parliamentary debates”</p> <p><strong>Josefina Eriksson</strong> (Uppsala University): “Are all ministers treated equally? Analyzing gendered patterns in interpellation debates”</p> <p><strong>Pierre Mesure</strong> (Ekonomistyrningsverket): “Using AI to make sense of public management data: Experiences from the Swedish National Financial Management Authority”</p> <p><strong>Fredrik Mohammadi Norén</strong> (Malmö University) &amp; <strong>Måns Magnusson</strong> (Uppsala University): “Swerik version 1.0 and beyond: A status report”</p> <p><strong>Faton Rekathati</strong> (KBLab): “Creating a multimodal parliamentary corpus: Connecting the Riksdag’s media recordings 1966–2002 to speech protocols”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[curation work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Swerik MP catalog is now available</title><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2024/The-Swerik-MP-catalog-is-now-available/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Swerik MP catalog is now available"/><published>2024-02-21T00:44:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-21T00:44:16+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2024/The-Swerik-MP-catalog-is-now-available</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2024/The-Swerik-MP-catalog-is-now-available/"><![CDATA[<p>Since the fall, the Swerik project has worked to improve the metadata for members of parliament, back to 1867. Besides having all MPs in our database, we also have full coverage of birth date and death date, gender, chamber, and more – including a much-improved coverage of party belonging. Here is a simple catalog list of all the MPs with some metadata (party belonging will be added soon): https://swerik-project.github.io/person-catalog/</p> <p>Important to note is that we build the Swerik MP database via Wikidata. Firstly, we extract MP metadata from various sources. Secondly, we upload this metadata on each MP-Wikidata page and, thirdly, we export the metadata from Wikidata that we want to include in the Swerik MP database. This makes it possible for other stakeholders (e.g. researchers, the Wikidata community, and citizens) to continue to build the MP database iteratively and openly, not bound to the specific agenda of the Swerik project.</p> <p>To secure the quality of the Swerik MP database, we have created different so-called unit tests with manually created metadata that we know are correct. If someone makes incorrect changes on Wikidata that conflict with these manual edits there will be a raised red flag and the database won’t be updated until we have made sure where the error is.</p> <p>Feel welcome to explore the Swerik MP catalog! Maybe you get curious about what the Liberal Brita Elmen and the Social Democrat Hildur Ericsson below did and said in parliament?</p> <p><img src="https://github.com/swerik-project/swerik-project.github.io/assets/15212990/aff3061f-6ee7-43bd-b36b-122a7ca00f8d" alt="Skärmavbild 2024-02-21 kl 13 16 47"/></p> <p><img src="https://github.com/swerik-project/swerik-project.github.io/assets/15212990/fc98c0e7-cc3a-4a5b-9516-0e6a427737cd" alt="Skärmavbild 2024-02-21 kl 13 17 26"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[curation work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Towards the correct number of MPs per Riksdag session</title><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Towards-_the_correct_number_of_MPs_per_Riksdag_session/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Towards the correct number of MPs per Riksdag session"/><published>2023-09-11T00:44:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-11T00:44:16+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Towards%20_the_correct_number_of_MPs_per_Riksdag_session</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Towards-_the_correct_number_of_MPs_per_Riksdag_session/"><![CDATA[<p>Counting members of parliament (MP) can be difficult. On the one hand, it is easy to find out how many members of parliament (MP) there should be in the parliament, and in each chamber for different decades. Over time, the number of Swedish MPs has changed for various reasons. For example, during the first years of the unicameral Riksdag, there were 350 MPs – a big mistake since the result sometimes generated 50 % votes for and 50 % against a proposed bill, which also happened in the so-called Lottery Riksdag 1973–1976. Since that, the number of MPs has been 349.</p> <p>Sorting out exactly which MPs were in the Riksdag and when, on the other hand, is more tricky, especially if you want to create a database structure. Currently, the Swerik project is working on this. We have all the parliamentary sessions and their dates, each represented by a Riksdag record (Riksdagsprotokoll), some 18,000 records since 1867. We also know how many MPs were represented in the Riksdag for each year. (Note: not how many MPs were present at each Riksdag meeting, since this could differ a lot.) The problem is that we don’t have full metadata coverage for the exact dates when MPs started and ended their terms in the Riksdag. Since we work with agile corpus curation, our first goal is to have at least 90 % coverage of MPs per Riksdag record.</p> <p>The first graph below shows the baseline of how many MPs there should be in the parliament, and the plots show our MP coverage in the database. Overall, 84 % of all the 18,000 Riksdag sessions have at least 90 % coverage. Hence, now we are trying to zoom in on some trouble years (16 %), defined in the second graph, which shows the number of Riksdag meetings per year (and chamber) that do not have at least 90 % MP coverage.</p> <p><img src="https://github.com/swerik-project/swerik-project.github.io/assets/15212990/1b3f9bca-c116-4eee-9288-ba1044f5298e" alt="2023-09-01"/> The baseline of MPs in the Swedish Riksdag 1867–2023 and the Swerik’s coverage of MPs per Riksdag meetings.</p> <p><img src="https://github.com/swerik-project/swerik-project.github.io/assets/15212990/0fc3e386-5e33-4d3e-9ab8-596b7d64de47" alt="image (5)"/> The graph shows the number of Riksdag meetings per year that have less than 90 % MP coverage in the Swerik database.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[curation work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Party formations and party splits in the Swedish Riksdag 1867–1970</title><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Party-formations-and-party-splits-in-the-Swedish-Riksdag-1867-1970/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Party formations and party splits in the Swedish Riksdag 1867–1970"/><published>2023-06-14T00:44:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T00:44:16+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Party-formations-and-party-splits-in-the-Swedish-Riksdag-1867%E2%80%931970</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Party-formations-and-party-splits-in-the-Swedish-Riksdag-1867-1970/"><![CDATA[<p>The phenomenon of political parties has existed for a long time, but the modern meaning of party is not as old. Today, a political party is synonymous with a party organization, which, among other things, is mobilized before general elections. At the time of the breakthrough of Swedish democracy around 1920, this phenomenon was quite new, at the time of the introduction of the bicameral Riksdag in 1867, it did not exist. In that sense, the Social Democrats are usually called Sweden’s first modern party, which emerged in the late 19th century.</p> <p>What a party was in the 19th century had a less fixed form, and such entities were often less permanent. Sometimes a party meant more or less a list that members signed up to signal what they intended to vote for. The image below shows party formations and party splits between 1867 and 1970, illustrated as a hierarchical tree (from the biographical book series Tvåkammarriksdagen 1867–1970).</p> <p>In the lower part of the tree, the five Riksdag parties are found that existed at the time of the dissolution of the Bicameral Riksdag, and which still exist today: Centre Party, Left Party, Liberals, Moderate Party, and Social Democrats. However, in the first decades of the Bicameral Riksdag there were a plethora of parties, and often with similar names. For example, within a 15-year period, you find “Centern” (second chamber, 1873–1882), “Center-högern” (second chamber, 1883–1886), “Nya centern” (second chamber, 1883–1887), and “Centern” (first chamber, 1885–1887).</p> <p>One aim of the Swerik project is to address this complexity and add “party belonging” (when such existed) to the database of members of parliaments.</p> <p><img width="1407" alt="Skärmavbild 2023-06-14 kl 10 37 55" src="https://github.com/swerik-project/swerik-project.github.io/assets/15212990/8fdfb9fd-c46c-4278-86c7-e1f126540991"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[curation work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The new and improved version (0.9) of the Swedish parliamentary debates is out!</title><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/The-new-and-improved-version-(0.9)-of-the-Swedish-parliamentary-debates-is-out!/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The new and improved version (0.9) of the Swedish parliamentary debates is out!"/><published>2023-05-30T00:44:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-30T00:44:16+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/The-new-and-improved-version-(0.9)-of-the-Swedish-parliamentary-debates-is-out!</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/The-new-and-improved-version-(0.9)-of-the-Swedish-parliamentary-debates-is-out!/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, the Swerik team has been improving the database of members of parliament (MP). We have now an almost complete catalog of all MPs that have had a position in the Swedish Riksdag, down to alternate member (ersättare) who only sat a couple of days in the parliament.</p> <p>Another important metadata feature that has improved in the MP database is the so-called i-ort (i riksdagen kallad) or “in the Riksdag called”. This is the geographical name of where an MP is from. The i-ort of Olof Palme, for instance, was for a while “Palme in Vällingby” (Palme i Vällingby). This system was used to distinguish different MPs with the same name, and that was especially important during the bicameral era (1867–1970), but also up until the 1990s.</p> <p>The improvement of i-ort has also pushed the quality of estimated accuracy for the identification of the speaker, that is the mapping of an MP speech with the corresponding MP in the database. This is shown in the graph below. From the 1920s, the accuracy is now often over 95 %. While improved significantly, we need to work more with the earlier decades, which we of course intend to do!</p> <p><img src="https://github.com/swerik-project/swerik-project.github.io/assets/15212990/fe5a299f-f3b9-403b-89c1-3a8a6b41861c" alt="image"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[New corpus version released]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Version 0.8 of the complete Swedish parliamentary debates 1867–2022 has been released</title><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Version-0.8-of-the-complete-Swedish-parliamentary-debates-1867-2022-has-been-released!/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Version 0.8 of the complete Swedish parliamentary debates 1867–2022 has been released"/><published>2023-05-03T00:44:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-03T00:44:16+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Version-0.8-of-the-complete-Swedish-parliamentary-debates-1867-2022-has-been-released!</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/Version-0.8-of-the-complete-Swedish-parliamentary-debates-1867-2022-has-been-released!/"><![CDATA[<p>When we submitted our RJ application in the spring of 2022, we had already created a pilot corpus of all Swedish parliamentary debates since 1920. This pre-work was conducted over a two-year period within the <a href="https://www.westac.se/en/">Welfare State Analytics project</a> and contained four main annotation tags: (1) speaker introduction, (2) matching the speaker introduction to the correct member of parliament (MP), (3) the speech text, and (4) the non-speech text (e.g. descriptions of activities in the chamber).</p> <p>We recurrently released improved versions of the annotated corpora through our agile corpus curation workflow in GitHub. Our initial aim was to reach 90 % accuracy in speaker identification, which we assessed as a good enough quality to start researching the material. To succeed in doing this, we used a combination of machine learning techniques and manual curation work.</p> <p>The graph below illustrates how the pilot corpus (often) improved regarding the estimated accuracy for identification of speakers in each version release, up until version 0.4.6.</p> <p><img width="474" alt="0 4 6" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/15212990/235863266-3b511a8c-ccfc-451d-8156-9ed066d845e3.png"/></p> <p>Now we have reached the 0.8 version, which includes the whole bicameral period (1867–1970) and unicameral period (1971–). The new thing is of course that we have the first version of the debates from 1867–1919. As shown from the graph below, the estimated accuracy for identification of speakers is often above 95 % for the period since 1920 but differs from 70–90 % for the earlier period (blue line). However, this is the first version of the whole speech corpus and we of course intend to continue working on the quality and release new versions with new improvements!</p> <p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/15212990/235863378-5b0872bd-b1b3-4f5b-bd80-b389726e62b2.png" alt="Skärmavbild 2023-04-12 kl 16 15 00"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[New corpus version released]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SWERIK has officially started!</title><link href="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/swerik-has-officially-started/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SWERIK has officially started!"/><published>2023-03-29T00:44:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-29T00:44:16+00:00</updated><id>https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/swerik-has-officially-started</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://swerik-project.github.io/blog/2023/swerik-has-officially-started/"><![CDATA[<p>SWERIK started officially on March 1, 2023, the same day when PI Fredrik Mohammadi Norén started his new position as an assistant professor in media and communication at Malmö University. However, the work of curating the Swedish parliamentary speeches has been going on since 2020 within the <a href="https://www.westac.se/en/">Welfare State Analytics project</a>, in which Fredrik, Måns Magnusson, and Väinö Yrjänäinen also work. Hence, a <a href="https://github.com/welfare-state-analytics/riksdagen-corpus">pilot corpus</a> of parliamentary speeches between 1920–2020 already existed when SWERIK started, with above 90 % estimated accuracy for the identification of speakers.</p> <p>Now, we have started to import speech data from 1867 to 1919. In version release 0.7, the corpus includes speech data from 1890 to today. Simultaneously, we continue to build the database with members of parliament (MP). The aim is to soon have all MPs in the database, which is a work we do in collaboration with Wikidata volunteers. Then we will start to add relevant metadata to MPs and improve the mapping of MPs to their speeches in the chambers.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[project starting up]]></summary></entry></feed>